<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Academic</title>
    <link>/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Academic</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Polyploid phylogenetics in plants: Insights on non-model organisms in Fabaceae and Malvaceae</title>
      <link>/publication/thesis2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/thesis2019/</guid>
      <description>Genome duplication is a common phenomenon in angiosperms and advances in sequencing technologies and bioinformatics is now revealing its prevalence and significance. In a polyploidization event all genes in a genome are doubled. Duplicated genes can take one of three paths, either both of the duplicated are maintained or one of them may be randomly lost or selected against. Polyploid species are challenging for resolving species relationships because of the number of duplicated genes and the different processes leading to genome reduction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Allele phasing is critical to revealing a shared allopolyploid origin of Medicago arborea and M. strasseri (Fabaceae)</title>
      <link>/publication/arborea_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/arborea_2018/</guid>
      <description>Background Whole genome duplication plays a central role in plant evolution. There are two main classes of polyploid formation: autopolyploids which arise within one species by doubling of similar homologous genomes; in contrast, allopolyploidy (hybrid polyploidy) arise via hybridization and subsequent doubling of nonhomologous (homoeologous) genomes. The distinction between polyploid origins can be made using gene phylogenies, if alleles from each genome can be correctly retrieved. We examined whether two closely related tetraploid Mediterranean shrubs (Medicago arborea and M.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A cryptic species produced by autopolyploidy and subsequent introgression involving Medicago prostrata (Fabaceae)</title>
      <link>/publication/cryptic_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/cryptic_2017/</guid>
      <description>Although hybridisation through genome duplication is well known, hybridisation without genome duplication (homoploid hybrid speciation, HHS) is not. Few well-documented cases have been reported. A possible instance of HHS in Medicago prostrata Jacq. was suggested previously, based on only two genes and one individual. We tested whether this species was formed through HHS by sampling eight nuclear loci and 22 individuals, with additional individuals from related species, using gene capture and Illumina sequencing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetic properties of 50 nuclear loci in Medicago (Leguminosae) generated using multiplexed sequence capture and next-generation sequencing</title>
      <link>/publication/filipe_2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 01:33:34 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/filipe_2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>